Alright, so בוקר טוב. Boker tov. Today's דף daf is י"ג, yud
gimmel, and we're starting at the beginning of
י"ג. yud gimmel. ואין תרומה אחר תרומה. ve'ein trumah achar trumah. So
it was an interesting משנה mishna that listed things that first started
a little unrelated, things that go לפי חשבון lefi cheshbon based on
proportion or based on the exact number, and then it talked about
things that A transfers to B and from B to C, so
that doesn't work by תמורה, tmura, it doesn't work the way תוספות
Tosafot understands by בית הפרס, beit hapras, you make one בית הפרס,
beit hapras, not the third one over, a תמורה tmura makes one
thing a תמורה tmura but it doesn't daisy chain. And now it's
a slightly different point, ואין תרומה אחר תרומה, ve'ein trumah achar trumah,
not that you can't go A to B and from B to
C, I mean, but that you cannot do two תרומות trumot on
the same thing. And in that way by the way I should
mention that it's different than תמורה, tmura, you can't do two תמורות
tmurot from the same original animal. You can have your original animal
you sanctified and do תמורה tmura to animal B, and then תמורה
tmura to animal C as long as you're starting always from A.
Okay, that's not daisy chaining it, but תרומה, trumah, once you take
תרומה trumah from the grain once, you can't take it a second
time. Let's take a look at what the חידוש chidush is, let's
look at the גמרא, Gemara, three lines from the top or four
lines from the top on י"ג עמוד א. yud gimmel amud aleph.
ואין תרומה אחר תרומה. ve'ein trumah achar trumah. מתניתין מן? matnitin man?
Rabbi Akiva. It's the
opinion of Rabbi Akiva, דתנן de'nan השותפין שתרמו זה אחר זה, hashutfim
she'tarmu zeh achar zeh, if you have partners, right, if it's one
person it's like an obvious case, you don't even have to mention
it. But let's say people are partners in a field and all
the grain is owned in partnership and then they took תרומה trumah
sequentially without consulting one another. Okay, so how do we interpret what
just happened? Now the reason it's an interesting question by תרומה trumah
is because by מעשר ma'aser there's an exact amount, ten percent. So
you have more of a basis to understand exactly what happened by
מעשר. ma'aser. Did the first guy take five percent and the next
guy five and they each did their half? Right, did the first
guy take ten then he did the whole thing? But by תרומה
trumah it's more of an open question because in theory the amount
is flexible although the Rabbis give some guidelines which will be brought
in a minute. So let's take a look. So the שותפין shutfim
took תרומה trumah sequentially and we don't know, you know, if they've
been in communication or not. Rabbi Eliezer אומר, omer, תרומת שניהם תרומה,
trumat shneihem trumah, they both work. Which is interesting, what does that
mean that they both work? Presumably that we interpret it that each
one has taken תרומה trumah on their portion of it. So we
view each one as taking תרומה trumah on his half. Okay, that's
what he says. Rabbi Akiva אומר omer אין תרומת שניהם תרומה. ein
trumat shneihem trumah. No, they both don't work. Now if they both
don't work that's very nice, but there's a couple of other possibilities.
At least the first one works, only the second one works, which
would be bizarre but maybe, or neither of them works.
רש"י Rashi suggests that neither of them works because the fact that
I had to go, if I was the second guy and take
it a second time shows that I didn't want you taking תרומה,
trumah, you know, we assume the תרומה trumah is taken on the
whole thing. The fact that I took it after you shows I
didn't want you taking on mine, and if I didn't want you
taking on mine then presumably you didn't want me taking on yours,
so none of them works. That's the way רש"י Rashi says, that's
the way both of them knew. But if the other one, one
of them didn't know, then right.
You could say that. תוספות Tosafot disagrees, תוספות Tosafot says that the
first one is good and the second one is no good, which
is the simpler understanding you would have of our משנה, mishna, although
the גמרא Gemara says that our משנה mishna is, yeah, משנה mishna
is Rabbi Akiva. So the simple read of our משנה, mishna, right,
our משנה mishna says there's no תרומה trumah after תרומה. trumah. You
don't normally assume our משנה mishna means and if you did it
twice nothing happened. You assume it means that if you did it
twice the second one was no good. So that's how תוספות Tosafot
reads Rabbi Akiva, it's certainly the easiest read. The first one is
assumed to have been done with the other partner's agreement and if
the other partner then comes along and does it himself a second
time, at this stage it is meaningless. That's the way תוספות Tosafot
reads it, which is consistent with the simple read of the משנה.
mishna. What's interesting is all the other times we say מתניתין לא
matnitin lo Rabbi Eliezer, and now we say מתניתין matnitin is Rabbi
Akiva when it disagrees with Rabbi Eliezer.
Well right,
because there's three opinions here. So we're actually, so the reason we
said Rabbi Akiva and not Rabbi Eliezer is because it's not Rabbi
Eliezer and it's not the third position, it's not the חכמים. Chachamim.
So let's read what the חכמים Chachamim say. וחכמים אומרים ve'chachamim omrim
אם תרם הראשון כשיעור im taram harishon kashiur אין תרומת השני תרומה.
ein trumat hasheni trumah.
If the second one did a normal amount, he just did within
the guidelines which was two percent, the average amount, then we assume
the second one, that was good and the second one didn't work,
and again that would be then consistent with our משנה. mishna. But
he doesn't say at all times there's a case where the second
one does work. ואם לא תרם כשיעור ve'im lo taram kashiur תרומת
השני תרומה. trumat hasheni trumah.
If he did not do the right amount, the second one works.
Now what does it mean that he did not do the right
amount? So רש"י Rashi says it means that he did not do
the average, he did the stingy amount. The stingy amount is not
two percent, it's one fiftieth, but it's one sixtieth. Okay, so now
the question is of course how do you read that he did
not do it and therefore what? And therefore according to רש"י Rashi
he would probably read it that I wasn't happy with what you
did, you did less than the average amount, we completely nullify what
you did, and then the question is is the second one alone
good? It's possible of course to read it again like no, that
I feel maybe you didn't take enough, so what you did was
acceptable but not sufficient. Anyway it's a little bit unclear what the
other exact possibilities are here. The easiest one seems to be Rabbi
Eliezer that says that we assume if both of them do it.
The first, the easiest one seems to be רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer
that says that if both of them do it, we interpret each
one doing an honest half. רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva also, רש"י Rashi
aside, seems to simply be saying once it was done, it was
done. The third one, which is that it's that if you didn't
do sufficient, you go by then it doesn't then then the first
one didn't work, it's still a little bit unclear or rather I
should say, how does it say it, then the second one does
work, it's a little unclear. The second one does work, does the
first one also work? And I'm adding to what you did or
I nullify what you did somehow I'm revealing that I did not
want you to do it at all. Okay, so there's a little
bit of a question of the last opinion. Those are the issues
about תרומה Terumah after תרומה. Terumah. Now we get back to ואין
תמורה עושה תמורה, Ve'ein Temurah Osah Temurah, which is back to the
daisy chain, which is like the בית הפרס. Bais HaPras. If you
made one thing a תמורה, Temurah, you can't make a תמורה Temurah
from a
תמורה. Temurah. מאי טעמא, Mai Ta'ama, what's the reason? אמר קרא, Amar
Kra, the פסוק Pasuk says, בתמורתו, Be'temurato, its תמורה, Temurah, of the
original thing you sanctified, ולא תמורת תמורתו, velo Temurat Temurato, not the
תמורה Temurah of the תמורה. Temurah. Okay, so the תורה Torah only
allows for תמורה Temurah from the original thing you sanctified, not from
the thing that was itself a תמורה. Temurah. ואין הולד עושה תמורה,
Ve'ein HaVlad Oseh Temurah, now the child of a קרבן Korban cannot
do a תמורה. Temurah. There's some parallel, the משנה Mishna made a
point of linking them together, and the parallel seems to be that
it's only the original קדושה, Kedusha, the thing you sanctified directly, not
something that has derivative קדושה. Kedusha. What has derivative קדושה? Kedusha? The
animal that's a תמורה Temurah or the animal that's a ולד Vlad
from the original. But רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda דאמר קרא, de'amar Kra,
הוא, Hu, הוא Hu ולא ולד. velo Vlad. It will, it and
the תמורה Temurah will be sanctified, it the original one, not the
child. Okay, so again, תמורה Temurah only works from the original. רבי
יהודה אומר הולד עושה תמורה. Rabbi Yehuda Omer HaVlad Oseh Temurah. He
distinguishes presumably between תמורה Temurah and ולד. Vlad. Maybe you can't make
a תמורה Temurah from a תמורה, Temurah, but you can make a
תמורה Temurah from a ולד. Vlad. דאמר קרא, de'amar Kra, יהיה. Yihiyeh.
The verse says it shall be, and that seems to be a
little extra.
קודש, Kodesh, why did it have to say יהיה? Yihiyeh? In Hebrew
you don't always need the verb, the to-be verb. So the Rabbis,
of a ולד, Vlad, that even something else becomes תמורה, Temurah, even
the ולד Vlad can be. So the ולד Vlad at least which
is a legitimate קדושה, Kedusha, although it's derivative, can be the source.
ורבנן Ve'Rabbanan and the Rabbis disagree. לרבות שוגג כמזיד lerabot Shogeg ke'Mezid
to include even if you are שוגג. Shogeg. Now what does שוגג
Shogeg mean? Well this is a whole discussion later on, but basic
point is that sometimes we say אין הקדש טעות. Ein Hekdesh Ta'os.
If you sanctified something accidentally, it's not good. It's not binding. However,
let's say you did תמורה Temurah accidentally. Accidentally we don't mean you
didn't know you were sinning, which presumably is always the case or
you're a real idiot if you understood the consequence would be you'd
transgress and you wouldn't accomplish your goal. But let's say you or
I said A is in exchange for B or whatever, this cow
is in exchange for that cow. I meant to say oh I
didn't actually mean this black cow, I actually meant the white cow.
I wasn't paying attention which one I was trying to exchange. Okay,
so if that was a הקדש Hekdesh case, I sanctified a cow
and I noticed oh wait a minute I had meant the other
one, not that one, that would be הקדש טעות. Hekdesh Ta'os. But
by תמורה, Temurah, even if there's a certain amount of error, nevertheless
the תמורה Temurah still is binding. Okay, so that is another example
in which תמורה Temurah is more binding than an original קדושה. Kedusha.
We have cases of בעל מום, Ba'al Mum, there are cases of
טעות Ta'os and so on. So that's we'll see more of that
later, that's what יהיה Yihiyeh comes to do. But again, what's interesting
to note is in the משנה, Mishna, the Rabbis respond to רבי
יהודה Rabbi Yehuda and they say basically no, תמורה Temurah doesn't make
a תמורה Temurah and a ולד Vlad doesn't make a תמורה. Temurah.
So those two are linked. And it seems that everybody agrees that
תמורה Temurah doesn't make a תמורה, Temurah, and the Rabbis' position seems
to be that there's the same logic. That the same way you
can't make a תמורה Temurah from a תמורה Temurah because it's not
the original, you can't make a תמורה Temurah from the ולד Vlad
because it also is not the original. Okay, so that is but
at least רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda does disagree by the case of
ולד. Vlad. We now turn to one last משנה Mishna of this
פרק. Perek. As I said, this פרק Perek is nice in that
it sort of goes through and a lot of the objects, the
people which are the objects. So we had a little bit of
a digression about תמורה עושה תמורה Temurah Osah Temurah and like linking
it to you know these whole a whole random collection, not so
random collection of ideas. But now we're back to straight תמורה Temurah
discussion about which objects. Next פרק Perek will also get us into
a much broader type of a range of cases, going way beyond
תמורה, Temurah, but here we are back to just listing types of
objects. So let's take a look at the next משנה. Mishna. העופות
והמנחות אין עושין תמורה. HaOfot VeHaMenachot Ein Osin Temurah.
You can't make תמורה Temurah from you remember you could do cows
and sheep and goats and even if you exchange two to one
or a hundred to one, but there are some things that you
don't do תמורה, Temurah, bird sacrifices and מנחות. Menachot. Why? Because the
תורה Torah says בהמה, Behemah, בהמה בבהמה. Behemah BiBehemah. Okay, and an
עוף Of is not considered a בהמה, Behemah, it's considered a bird,
not an animal, or you know בהמה Behemah meaning a land animal,
and מנחות Menachot are certainly not livestock. So therefore the תורה Torah
only describes it by בהמה, Behemah, not by birds.
אין עושין תמורה. Ein Osin Temurah. שלא נאמר אלא בהמה. Shelo Ne'emar
Ela Behemah. It says בהמה. Behemah. Presumably therefore also, although it's not
made explicit, but they also presumably cannot be the object, they cannot
be the substitute either. They can't be the original object and it's
בהמה בבהמה. Behemah BiBehemah. So if you try to exchange your sheep
which was a קרבן Korban for a bird, that would also presumably
not be תמורה Temurah because it has both sides have to be
a בהמה. Behemah. So that's that is one thing that's excluded. And
now we talk about the another category of excluded has to do
with the ownership of the קרבן, korban, and we related to this
before. הציבור והשותפים אינם עושים תמורה. hatzibur vehashutfim einam osim tmura. We
don't do תמורה tmura if it is a קרבן, korban, a קרבן
ציבור korban tzibur like a תמיד tamid or a מוסף, musaf, something
that is brought on behalf of the whole community, or it's owned
in partnership. Michael and I get together and decide we can't each
of us afford an עולה ola but together we'll jointly give an
עולה. ola. We're able to do that. But in that case you
cannot do a תמורה. tmura.
Even if both of us do it together.
Even if we do it together. שנאמר, shene'emar, לא יחליפנו ולא ימיר,
lo yachalifenu velo yamir, you shall not singular exchange it or substitute
or exchange it. So יחיד עושה תמורה, yachid oseh tmura, the verb
is in the singular, only a person, an individual can do it,
ואין ציבור ושותפים עושים תמורה, ve'ein tzibur vehashutfim osim tmura, not partners
or the community at large. קדשי בדק הבית אינם עושים תמורה. kodshei
bedek habayit einam osim tmura. Also what we've been assuming for the
last few דפים dappim is that it has to be קרבן korban
sanctity. Not a sanctity for the temple treasury. We even learned even
if you originally sanctified an animal with a blemish, so it was
קדושת דמים לעולה למזבח kedushas damim l'ola l'mizbe'ach that you had to,
it never actually was intrinsic קרבן korban sanctity, but you were going
to use the proceeds to buy a קרבן, korban, even that would
not do a תמורה, tmura, only something that was had real קדושת
הגוף, kedushas haguf, was really had intrinsic קרבן korban sanctity. Okay, so
this is talking about the other extreme which is it was straight
as a gift to the בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, but we've even
dealt with middle cases which are also excluded. So קדשי בדק הבית
אינם עושים תמורה. kodshei bedek habayit einam osim tmura. If you do
it for the temple treasury, no תמורה, tmura, it has to be
a קרבן. korban. אמר רבי שמעון, Amar Rabbi Shimon, and now אמר
רבי שמעון Amar Rabbi Shimon is going to not disagree but use
a פסוק pasuk to base it on. והרי מעשר בכלל היה. v'harei
ma'aser bichlal haya. When if you look the Torah at the end
of בחוקותי Bechukosai first says don't do תמורה tmura and then a
few פסוקים pesukim later it says and by the way you have
to give מעשר, ma'aser, וכל מעשר בקר וצאן עשירי יהיה קודש להשם.
vechol ma'aser bakar vatzon asiri yihiyeh kodesh l'Hashem.
Then it says again לא יחליפנו ולא ימיר אותו טוב ברע. lo
yachalifenu velo yamir oso tov b'ra.
So when it does מעשר ma'aser it a second time tells you
don't do תמורה tmura when it's dealing with מעשר. ma'aser. Why is
it repeating it by מעשר? ma'aser? So he says והרי מעשר בכלל
היה, v'harei ma'aser bichlal haya, it was in the general category of
תמורה. tmura. ולמה יצא, v'lama yatza, why was it singled out? לומר
לך, lomar lecha, to use it as an example of the types
of things you do תמורה tmura on. מה מעשר קרבן יחיד, mah
ma'aser korban yachid, the same way מעשר ma'aser is an individual's קרבן,
korban, יצאו קרבנות ציבור. yatzu korbanos tzibur.
So only an individual קרבן korban has תמורה, tmura, not a communal
ציבור, tzibur, not a communal קרבן. korban. ומה מעשר קרבן מזבח, u'mah
ma'aser korban mizbe'ach,
and the same way מעשר ma'aser is a sacrifice, something that goes
on the altar, יצאו קרבנות בדק הבית. yatzu korbanos bedek habayit. So
that excludes things that are given, although he uses a funny phrase,
קרבנות korbanos to the temple treasury, here קרבן korban means gifts. And
that's exactly going to be his point, that the תנא קמא Tanna
Kamma excluded it from, assumed that the word קרבן korban excluded gifts
to the temple. And he says no no no, the word קרבן
korban can refer to a gift to the temple. So how do
I know to exclude things that are going to בדק הבית? bedek
habayit? Because מעשר ma'aser is the paradigm and therefore מעשר ma'aser tells
me private and מעשר ma'aser tells me קרבן korban to the altar,
not a gift to the temple. So he doesn't, in here in
the משנה Mishnah there's no disagreement, it's just a question of where
he learns it from. In the גמרא Gemara there might be some
subtle differences. Let's take a look at the גמרא. Gemara. תנו רבנן.
Tanu Rabbanan.
יכול יהיו קדשי בדק הבית עושים תמורה, yachol yehu kodshei bedek habayit
osim tmura, perhaps things sanctified to the temple treasury would make a
תמורה. tmura. תלמוד לומר Talmud lomar קרבן, korban, no it says if
you that it's a קרבן korban that if you're sanctifying an animal
for a קרבן, korban, then it says do not make a תמורה.
tmura. So only things that are a קרבן, korban, not gifts to
the temple treasury. יצאו קדשי בדק הבית שלא נקראו קרבן. yatzu kodshei
bedek habayit shelo nikra korban. So those are not called a קרבן
korban and therefore they're excluded from קרבן. korban. Not רבי שמעון, Rabbi
Shimon, רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon learned it from מעשר. ma'aser. Presumably this
is the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma who just says קרבן korban that
excludes gifts to the treasury. So the גמרא Gemara says ולא, v'lo,
is that really true that a gift to the treasury is not
called a קרבן? korban? והתניא, vehatanya, we learned in a ברייתא, braisa,
אי קרבן, ee korban, if you want me to learn out from
the word קרבן korban to exclude gifts to the temple, שומע אני
אפילו קדשי בדק הבית, shome'a ani afilu kodshei bedek habayit, I might
have included gifts to the treasury from the word קרבן. korban. Why?
שנקראו קרבן, shenikru korban, they are called a
קרבן. korban. כעניין שנאמר, ke'inyan shene'emar, ונקרב את קרבן השם, vanakrev es
korban Hashem, when the after the war with מדין, Midian, when the
officers came to offer up the, you know, a portion from the
booty from מדין, Midian, they call it the gift to God, they
call it קרבן השם. korban Hashem. So קרבן korban is a word
that you can use for a gift, a gift to the temple
treasury, even not a קרבן. korban. So the word קרבן korban would
not have excluded a gift to the treasury. So therefore תלמוד לומר,
Talmud lomar, so how do I know to exclude? Now this by
the way is not this פסוק pasuk that we're talking about, this
ברייתא braisa is not about תמורה. tmura. This ברייתא braisa is about
שחוטי חוץ, shechutei chutz, שחוטי
חוץ shechutei chutz a קרבן korban outside the בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash.
So it says if you have a קרבן korban להשם אל פתח
אהל מועד לא הביאו, l'Hashem el pesach ohel mo'ed lo hevi'o, you
know, if you slaughtered your קרבן korban outside of the temple and
didn't bring it to the temple, then you're חייב כרת chayav kares
for slaughtering a קרבן korban outside the temple. So what this ברייתא
braisa wants to know is let's say you slaughtered an animal that
was sanctified to the temple treasury, is that also שחוטי חוץ? shechutei
chutz? And clearly you're destroying הקדש. hekdesh. It's not accepted, but is
it also שחוטי חוץ? shchutei chutz? Okay, so again it's a question
whether the תורה Torah is talking only about קרבנות korbanos or even
about things sanctified to the treasury. Not about תמורה, tmura, but about
שחוטי חוץ. shchutei chutz. So it says like this: maybe if it
just says קרבן korban I would have included temple treasury. תלמוד לומר
talmud lomar so the verse says ואל פתח אהל מועד לא הביאו.
v'el pesach ohel moed lo heveio. No, it says the problem of
slaughtering it outside the temple was you didn't bring it to the
temple. כל הבא אל פתח אהל מועד חייבין עליו משום שחוטי חוץ.
kol haba el pesach ohel moed chayavin alav mishum shchutei chutz. Things
that would normally come to the temple, you're liable for slaughtering outside
the temple.
וכל שאינו בא אל פתח אהל מועד אין חייבין עליו משום שחוטי
חוץ. v'chol she'eino ba el pesach ohel moed ein chayavin alav mishum
shchutei chutz. You would not be חייבין chayavin outside. Now why would
you normally not bring it to the temple? So the easiest reason
is because it's not a קרבן, korban, because it's not sanctified for
the altar. But there's another reason as well. If you remember from
our earlier discussion, what are the only types of animals you're supposed
to sanctify to the temple treasury? Animals that have a blemish, right?
If it's unblemished you're not allowed to sanctify to the temple treasury
or
something you can't bring on the altar.
Fine. Anyway, so either way, either it has a blemish or it's
not even fit for the altar because it's a camel, it does
not belong in the temple. Okay, so therefore it's clear from context
that you're חייב chayav only when you slaughter something that was sanctified
for the altar, not something that was sanctified for the temple treasury.
All right, so now I left the גמרא Gemara downstairs. Anyway,
so now what do you see? You see that the word קרבן
korban in this ברייתא braisa did not exclude temple treasury. They had
to learn it from the rest of the verse that says you
didn't bring it to the אהל מועד. ohel moed. All right, so
therefore how can our ברייתא braisa say that קרבן korban for תמורה
tmura excludes בדק הבית? bedek habayis? So let's take a look. The
גמרא Gemara says like this: אלמא איקרי קרבן. alma ikri korban. You
see that קרבן korban would be included בדק הבית. bedek habayis. So
how does our ברייתא braisa assume they're excluded for תמורה? tmura? So
אמר רבי חנינא לא קשיא. amar Rabbi Chanina lo kashya. It's not
difficult. הא רבי שמעון הא רבנן. ha Rabbi Shimon ha rabanan. It's
that exactly the debate of רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon and the רבנן.
rabanan. לרבי שמעון איקרי קרבן לרבנן לא איקרי קרבן. l'Rabbi Shimon ikri
korban l'rabanan lo ikri korban. רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon says that the
ברייתא braisa that says that they would be included in קרבן korban
is רבי שמעון. Rabbi Shimon. That's why רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon needed
to learn from מעשר. maaser. How does רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon exclude
בדק הבית bedek habayis and exclude ציבור? tzibur? He doesn't learn it
from, you know, he learns it from the מעשר maaser is the
paradigm. The רבנן rabanan exclude it from other verses. They exclude individual
from the use of the singular and they exclude בדק הבית bedek
habayis from the use of קרבן. korban. So what do we have?
We have the following: in our משנה mishna רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon
learns from מעשר, maaser, the רבנן rabanan don't tell us where they
learn it from. The גמרא Gemara quotes a ברייתא braisa that learns
from the word קרבן korban to exclude בדק הבית. bedek habayis. The
גמרא Gemara says but we have another ברייתא braisa that says that
קרבן korban includes בדק הבית bedek habayis and you need something else
to exclude. So it says that's exactly the debate of רבי שמעון
Rabbi Shimon and the רבנן. rabanan. The רבנן rabanan exclude it from
קרבן. korban. רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon says קרבן korban could mean בדק
הבית bedek habayis and that's why he has to use מעשר maaser
as his paradigm. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says like this: לרבנן
לא
איקרי קרבן. l'rabanan lo ikri korban. And
how could the רבנן rabanan say that קרבן korban is does not
include בדק הבית? bedek habayis? What about the verse we quoted? והקרבנו
את קרבן ה׳ v'hikravnu es korban Hashem and
we brought the קרבן korban of God and that's talking about something
donated to the temple treasury.
So the גמרא Gemara
says: קרבן ה׳ איקרי. korban Hashem ikri. A קרבן korban of God
it's called. קרבן לה׳ לא איקרי. korban l'Hashem lo ikri. A קרבן
korban to God, right. But the point is it's extremely rare that
קרבן korban means a gift. So the fact that one place in
the תורה Torah it meant a gift to the treasury rather than
a sacrifice, we're going to try to limit it. So it limits
it by saying there it has a modifier קרבן ה׳, korban Hashem,
it doesn't say קרבן korban סתם, stam, it doesn't say קרבן לה׳.
korban l'Hashem. You can use Bar-Ilan and see if anywhere else in
the תורה Torah it says קרבן ה׳, korban Hashem, but the גמרא
Gemara presumably felt safe in saying that when it says that, it
means treasury. Okay, so there you have it. So רבי שמעון Rabbi
Shimon prefers to learn from מעשר maaser as his paradigm. He learns
everything from מעשר. maaser. The רבנן rabanan are not focusing on that
and therefore they learn to be excluded from the word קרבן korban
excludes בדק הבית. bedek habayis. רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon feels קרבן korban
is not limited enough and he has to learn from מעשר maaser
as his paradigm. Okay, now we go on.
תנו רבנן. tanu rabanan. So we have a
ברייתא. braisa. לא יבקר בין טוב לרע ולא ימירנו. lo yivaker bein
tov l'ra v'lo yemirenu. Do not choose between good and evil and
do not exchange it. למה נאמר? lama ne'emar? Why does it have
to say it again? והלא כבר נאמר לא יחליפנו ולא ימיר אותו
טוב ברע או רע בטוב? v'halo kvar ne'emar lo yachlifenu v'lo yamir
oso tov b'ra o ra b'tov? So now again it asks why
the תורה Torah repeated the prohibition by מעשר. maaser. It said it
once generally and then it repeated it by מעשר. maaser. So we
know what רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon would say because מעשר maaser is
the paradigm. But let's take a
look. לפי שנאמר לא יחליפנו ולא ימירנו. lefi shene'emar lo yachlifenu v'lo
yemirenu. משמע קרבן יחיד וקרבן ציבור. mashma korban yachid v'korban tzibur. I
might have thought that the original prohibition of תמורה tmura applied whether
it's an individual קרבן, korban, whether it's communal. וקרבן מזבח וקרבן בדק
הבית. v'korban mizbeach v'korban bedek habayis. Whether it's going to the altar,
whether it's a gift to the temple treasury. Right, I would have
said it applies to everything. תלמוד לומר talmud lomar so therefore it
says a second time. לא יבקר. lo yivaker. That's why it says
a second time by מעשר maaser to use מעשר maaser as the
paradigm. So this is all רבי שמעון. Rabbi Shimon. אמר רבי שמעון
amar Rabbi Shimon said רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon meaning the whole thing
is רבי שמעון. Rabbi Shimon. הרי מעשר בכלל היה. harei ma'aser baklal
haya. Now I'm going to tell you what, now this is why
it said it again by מעשר, ma'aser, because מעשר ma'aser was in
the general umbrella of all, under the umbrella of all things you
can't do תמורה. temurah. למה יצא? Lama yatza? Why did the Torah
repeat it, the prohibition of תמורה temurah specifically by מעשר? ma'aser? I
would have anyway known that it applied to מעשר. ma'aser. לומר לך,
Lomar lecha, the reason it was repeated by מעשר ma'aser is to
tell you that מעשר ma'aser is the paradigm. מה מעשר קרבן יחיד
וקרבן מזבח, Ma ma'aser korban yachid vekorban mizbeach, the same way מעשר
ma'aser is a private קרבן korban and it goes on the altar,
ודבר שבא בחובה, vedavar sheba bechova, here's a new thing we haven't
seen yet, something that comes through obligation, we'll discuss that in a
minute, ודבר שאינו בשותפות, vedavar she'eino beshutfus, and it's not in partnership,
which is similar to the idea of it individual, it's not communal,
it's not partnership, אף כל, af kol, so therefore also all תמורה,
temurah, קרבן יחיד וקרבן מזבח ודבר שבא בחובה, korban yachid vekorban mizbeach
vedavar sheba bechova, it's only individual, it's only something that goes on
the altar, it's only something that comes as an obligation, we'll talk
about that in a minute, ודבר שאינו בא בשותפות, vedavar she'eino ba
beshutfus, and not in partnership. So he learns it all out from
מעשר, ma'aser, that's why the Torah repeated it by מעשר ma'aser to
tell you use מעשר ma'aser as your paradigm. Now the rabbis who
don't learn it from מעשר, ma'aser, and we don't know why they
would say the Torah repeats it by, at least not yet, where
do they learn these same laws? So that it's not law that
it's not communal or it's not partnership they learn from the Torah's
use of the singular verb. The law that it's only sacrifices on
the altar and not בדק הבית, bedek habayis, they say the word
קרבן korban
sufficiently excludes things that are going to the to the temple treasury.
The only thing we don't know whether they where they learn it
out or whether they agree is this new הלכה halacha of it
has to come בחובה bechova through an obligation. We'll see in a
minute what that means and we'll see if the rabbis agree to
that or not. Let's take a look. רבי אומר, Rebbi omer, said
Rebbi. למה יצאת מעשר מן הכלל? Lama yatzas ma'aser min haklal? Rebbi
says, he seems to be saying an opposing position or at least
an alternative, that we do not necessarily emphasize that the reason it
says מעשר ma'aser is to tell you that מעשר ma'aser serves as
the paradigm for תמורה. temurah. I'll tell you something else about מעשר,
ma'aser, why מעשר ma'aser is singled out. לידון בתמורת שמו ובתמורת גופו,
Lidon bitmuras shemo uvitmuras gufo,
because מעשר ma'aser has a special הלכה. halacha. You might remember from
when we learned בכורות, Bechoros, there's this funny or this fun, I
should say not funny, fun הלכה halacha by מעשר, ma'aser, which is
that you if you miscall certain things ten, they also become מעשר.
ma'aser. If you call nine ten and eleven ten, they all become
מעשר. ma'aser. Only one off. Actually there's a different הלכה. halacha. Nine,
because you haven't yet designated מעשר, ma'aser, so nine when you called
it ten, it's נאכל במומו. ne'echal bemumo. You can never bring it
as a קרבן, korban, it has קדושת מעשר kedushas ma'aser but you
actually wait till it gets a blemish, eat it out of the
בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. If you call eleven ten, since מעשר ma'aser
already exists, that's a little more powerful, calling eleven ten, or it
might be said the opposite, it's most obviously not מעשר, ma'aser, something
else is מעשר, ma'aser, so the status of calling eleven ten is
that it gives it the קדושה kedusha of a שלמים. shelamim. Even
though you said ten, it can't be מעשר, ma'aser, there's already a
מעשר, ma'aser, so it has the status of a שלמים shelamim and
you bring it as a קרבן. korban. So מעשר ma'aser has, can,
it's similar to תמורה, temurah, right? תמורה, Temurah, you have something sanctified
and you connect it to another animal, you try to transfer it,
and תמורת גופו, tmuras gufo, you exchange the body and they both
become קדוש. kadosh. Here you didn't try to transfer the body as
it were, but you did תמורת שמו. tmuras shemo. You misgave its
name to the wrong thing. You tried to essentially transfer its name
to number nine or eleven. And that also, there you didn't transgress,
and that also there also that has קדושה. kedusha. So תמורת שמו
tmuras shemo is similar to תמורת גופו. tmuras gufo. So Rebbi is
saying that's why the Torah repeats תמורה temurah by מעשר. ma'aser. Since
it innovates this idea of תמורת שמו, tmuras shemo, which we learn
from a different פסוק, pasuk, therefore you might have thought, I'm going
to sort of flesh out what the גמרא Gemara is about to
say, you might have thought that when something is given a special
status, maybe it's taken completely out of its previous group. Meaning, since
the Torah says that by מעשר ma'aser we have this new concept
called תמורת שמו, tmuras shemo, exchanging the name, maybe תמורת גופו tmuras
gufo no longer applies. Okay? Maybe it's only תמורת שמו, tmuras shemo,
not תמורת גופו. tmuras gufo. So the reason the Torah repeated תמורה
temurah by מעשר ma'aser was not as Rabbi Shimon says to make
it a paradigm, but was to insist that although it also has
תמורת שמו, tmuras shemo, it still also has, remained, retained its תמורת
גופו. tmuras gufo. Okay, so let's take a look.
I'm sorry, please wait.
So you still can do if you do תמורה temurah with מעשר,
ma'aser, you transgress and the second, of course that's explicit in the
Torah, that's the one thing mentioned in the פסוק, pasuk, right? But
don't think that just because it has תמורת שמו, tmuras shemo, somehow
it has, it's different and it no longer has תמורת גופו. tmuras
gufo. Okay? לידון בתמורת שמו ובתמורת גופו, Lidon bitmuras shemo uvitmuras gufo,
both apply. לומר לך, Lomar lecha, to tell you, תמורת שמו tmuras
shemo and now, the הגהות הב"ח hagahos habach points out it's really
like ולומר לך. velomar lecha. So number one is תמורת גופו tmuras
gufo applies. Number two is, here are some of the הלכות halachos
in actually the way that they're different. So the first thing the
reason the Torah repeated to tell you it applies, here are some
differences by the way. ולומר לך, Velomar lecha, it also tells you
the following thing. תמורת שמו קריבה תמורת גופו אינה קריבה. Tmuras shemo
kriva tmuras gufo einah kriva. If you do תמורת שמו, tmuras shemo,
you bring it as a קרבן. korban. If you do תמורת גופו,
tmuras gufo, you do not. You might remember that one of the
הלכות halachos that we learned this from בכור bechor is that תמורת
בכור tmuras bechor and תמורת מעשר tmuras ma'aser are not brought as
קרבן. korban. Normally תמורה temurah is brought as
קרבן, korban, not
תמורת בכור. tmuras bechor. What's unique about בכור Bekhor and
מעשר? Ma'aser? Yeah. קדוש. Kadosh. What?
Well, בכור Bekhor by itself, you don't instill it, but not only,
but מעשר Ma'aser you do, but both of their identity is defined
not just by instilling, which you could in theory do to any
animal, their identity is defined by a certain reality. This was, right,
so an event, this was the firstborn, this was the tenth. So
when you transfer the קדושה kedusha to another animal, it has this
קדושת בכור, kedushat Bekhor, it has this קדושת מעשר, kedushat Ma'aser, but
it is not a בכור, Bekhor, it is not a מעשר. Ma'aser.
It wasn't the tenth, it wasn't the first, it wasn't the tenth
out of the gate, it wasn't the firstborn to its mother. So
because it has the קדושה kedusha without being the thing itself, the
הלכה halakha is that תמורת בכור tmurat Bekhor and תמורת מעשר tmurat
Ma'aser are not brought as a קרבן. korban. Normal תמורה tmura is,
but תמורת בכור tmurat Bekhor and תמורת מעשר tmurat Ma'aser are not.
Now, if I accidentally say eleven is ten, the הלכה halakha is
that it's not מעשר, Ma'aser, it's שלמים. shlamim. So שלמים shlamim I
might bring it as a קרבן. korban. So that's one difference. Okay,
תמורת שמו tmurat shemo קרבה, kreva, when I call eleven ten, I
bring it as a קרבן. korban. When I call nine ten, actually
I don't, but I wait for it to get a blemish. When
I call eleven ten, it's a שלמים shlamim and I bring it.
תמורת גופו tmurat gufo אינה קרבה. eina kreva. If I do a
normal תמורה tmura of exchange, it's not brought because then it has
קדושת מעשר kedushat Ma'aser without being מעשר, Ma'aser, and we learn from
בכור Bekhor that I do not bring it as a קרבן. korban.
So that's a way in which they're different. Now, another way: תמורת
שמו tmurat shemo נגאלת, nigelet, תמורת גופו tmurat gufo אינה נגאלת. eina
nigelet. What does the תורה Torah say by מעשר? Ma'aser? לא יגאל.
lo yiga'el. It cannot be redeemed, which means if it gets a
blemish, you eat it with its blemish, but you don't redeem it.
So if you have תמורת גופו, tmurat gufo, you then it has
actual real קדושת מעשר. kedushat Ma'aser. So what's the הלכה halakha of
קדושת מעשר? kedushat Ma'aser? You can't redeem it. If it gets a
blemish, you eat it outside the בית המקדש, Beit HaMikdash, but you
don't redeem it. If it's תמורת שמו, tmurat shemo, what did I
just tell you happens to תמורת שמו? tmurat shemo? When you call
eleven ten, it doesn't become מעשר, Ma'aser, it becomes שלמים. shlamim. Oh,
well שלמים, shlamim, if it gets a blemish, you can redeem it.
Okay, so there are these differences. But again, the key here of
the two differences is that תמורת שמו tmurat shemo becomes a שלמים.
shlamim. Because it becomes a שלמים, shlamim, therefore you bring it as
a קרבן korban and therefore you can redeem it. Because תמורת גופו
tmurat gufo is מעשר. Ma'aser. Because it's מעשר, Ma'aser, number one, you
can't redeem it, you eat it with a blemish, and number two,
because it's קדושת מעשר kedushat Ma'aser without being real מעשר, Ma'aser, you
can't bring it as a קרבן. korban. Okay, so let's read that
again. תמורת שמו tmurat shemo נגאלת, nigelet, when you do the wrong
name, you call eleven ten, it's a שלמים shlamim and therefore you
can redeem it if it has a blemish. תמורת גופו tmurat gufo
אינה נגאלת. eina nigelet. תמורת גופו tmurat gufo is קדושת מעשר, kedushat
Ma'aser, you can't redeem קדושת מעשר. kedushat Ma'aser. You eat it as
a קרבן korban outside the בית המקדש. Beit HaMikdash. תמורת גופו tmurat
gufo חלה על דבר הראוי ועל דבר שאינו ראוי. hala al davar
ha-ra'uy ve-al davar she-eino ra'uy. Now, תמורת גופו, tmurat gufo, what's the
הלכה halakha of תמורה? tmura? You'll remember that one of the ways
תמורה tmura is more powerful than הקדש hekdesh is that if you
do תמורה tmura on something with a blemish, it really gets קדושת
מזבח. kedushat mizbe'ach. You can't bring it as a קרבן, korban, but
it gets real קדושת מזבח. kedushat mizbe'ach. Okay, you have to redeem
it and so on and use the money and use the proceeds
for a קרבן. korban. So that is תמורת גופו. tmurat gufo. תמורת
שמו, tmurat shemo, if when I call eleven ten, I make it
a שלמים, shlamim, that's like an original קדושה. kedusha. That's not תמורה.
tmura. So let's say eleven had a blemish. What would be the
status? It's like I took a normal animal with a blemish and
I called it a שלמים. shlamim. So in that type of a
case, it has
קדושת דמים למזבח. kedushat damim la-mizbe'ach. You're still going to use the
proceeds, but it doesn't get real קדושת הגוף. kedushat ha-guf. Okay, that's
like just sanctifying an animal with a blemish. So let's read that
again. תמורת גופו, tmurat gufo, if you do a real תמורה, tmura,
חלה על דבר הראוי ועל דבר שאינו ראוי. hala al davar ha-ra'uy
ve-al davar she-eino ra'uy. It takes effect whether the animal has a
blemish or not. Again, with a blemish obviously you won't bring it
as a קרבן, korban, but it has real קדושת קרבן kedushat korban
and there are relevant aspects to that, like if you redeem it,
you still can't shear it and work it, etc. ותמורת שמו, ve-tmurat
shemo, if you're calling eleven ten and you essentially are making it
a שלמים, shlamim, but it's an original sanctification because you're now calling
it ten, אינה חלה אלא על דבר הראוי בלבד. eina hala ela
al davar ha-ra'uy bilvad. It only really takes effect on an animal
without a blemish. It does not take effect on an animal with
a blemish, or certainly not to the same extent. Hold on, let
me just double-check רש"י Rashi about
that. One minute. Right, right, right. רש"י Rashi says it doesn't mean
it's not sanctified at all, it means it's like you
called an animal with a blemish a שלמים. shlamim. So what's the
status? It means you sell it, the proceeds are used for a
קרבן, korban, but it never gets a real intrinsic קדושת הגוף. kedushat
ha-guf. Okay, so anyway, that is the nice statement of רבי. Rebbi.
It's fascinating to line those up and to make that analogy and
comparison between calling eleven ten, which is a type of an exchange,
and between trying to exchange the bodies, and there are differences between
the way you do it. In one case, the basic rule of
the difference is calling eleven ten, you made it a שלמים, shlamim,
so it has all the הלכות halakhot of just making an animal
a שלמים. shlamim. It doesn't really take the same effect if it
has a blemish, but you can redeem it, you can bring it
as a קרבן, korban, whereas doing the תמורה tmura has all the
special הלכות halakhot of תמורה. tmura.
But you can't make it a תמורה. tmura.
*Rabbi Meir:* רבי מאיר. Rabbi Meir. *Rabbi Yehuda:* רבי יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda.
*Rabbi Shimon:* רבי שמעון. Rabbi Shimon. *Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak:* רב נחמן
בר יצחק. Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak. *Rava:* רבא. Rava. *Rashi:* רש"י. Rashi.
*Pasuk:* פסוק. pasuk. *Ma'aser:* מעשר. ma'aser. *Halacha:* הלכה. halacha. *Chiddush:* חידוש. chiddush.
*In:* אין. In. *Daf:* דף. daf. *Neder:* נדר. neder. *Stam:* סתם. stam.
*Ba be'chovah:* בא בחובה. ba be'chovah. *Amlei:* אמר ליה. Amlei. *Olas nedavah:*
עולת נדבה. olas nedavah. *Rabbi:* רבי. Rebbi. *Torah:* תורה. Torah. *Gemara:* גמרא.
Gemara. *Mishnah:* משנה. mishnah. *Bechoros:* בכורות. Bechoros. *Temurah:* תמורה. temurah. *Hekdesha:* הקדשה.
hekdesha. *Shelamim:* שלמים. Shelamim. *Rabbi Meir:* רבי מאיר.
Rabbi Meir. *Rabbi Yehuda:* רבי יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda. *Rabbi Shimon:* רבי שמעון.
Rabbi Shimon. *Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak:* רב נחמן בר יצחק. Rav Nachman
bar Yitzchak. *Rava:* רבא. Rava. *Rashi:* רש"י. Rashi. *Pasuk:* פסוק. pasuk. *Ma'aser:*
מעשר. ma'aser.
*Halacha:* הלכה. halacha. *Chiddush:* חידוש.
chiddush. *In:* אין. In. *Daf:* דף. daf. *Neder:* נדר. neder. *Stam:* סתם.
stam. *Ba be'chovah:* בא בחובה.
ba be'chovah. *Amlei:* אמר ליה. Amlei. *Olas nedavah:* עולת נדבה. olas nedavah.
*Rabbi:* רבי. Rebbi. *Torah:* תורה. Torah. *Gemara:* גמרא. Gemara. *Mishnah:* משנה. mishnah.
*Bechoros:* בכורות. Bechoros. *Temurah:* תמורה. temurah. *Hekdesha:* הקדשה. hekdesha. *Shelamim:* שלמים. Shelamim.
*Rabbi Meir:* רבי מאיר. Rabbi Meir. *Rabbi Yehuda:* רבי יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda.
*Rabbi Shimon:* רבי שמעון. Rabbi Shimon. *Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak:* רב נחמן
בר יצחק. Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak.
*Rava:* רבא. Rava. *Rashi:* רש"י. Rashi. *Pasuk:* פסוק.
pasuk. *Ma'aser:* מעשר. ma'aser. *Halacha:* הלכה. halacha. *Chiddush:* חידוש. chiddush. *In:* אין.
In. *Daf:* דף. daf. *Neder:* נדר. neder. *Stam:* סתם. stam. *Ba be'chovah:*
בא בחובה. ba be'chovah. *Amlei:* אמר ליה. Amlei. *Olas nedavah:* עולת נדבה.
olas nedavah. *Rabbi:* רבי. Rebbi. *Torah:* תורה. Torah. *Gemara:* גמרא. Gemara. *Mishnah:*
משנה. mishnah. *Bechoros:* בכורות. Bechoros. *Temurah:* תמורה. temurah. *Hekdesha:* הקדשה. hekdesha. *Shelamim:*
שלמים. Shelamim. *Rabbi Meir:* רבי מאיר. Rabbi Meir. *Rabbi Yehuda:* רבי יהודה.
Rabbi Yehuda. *Rabbi Shimon:* רבי שמעון. Rabbi Shimon. *Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak:*
רב נחמן
בר יצחק.
Rav
Nachman bar Yitzchak. *Rava:* רבא. Rava. *Rashi:* רש"י. Rashi. *Pasuk:* פסוק. pasuk.
*Ma'aser:* מעשר. ma'aser. *Halacha:* הלכה. halacha. *Chiddush:* חידוש. chiddush. *In:* אין. In.
*Daf:* דף. daf. *Neder:* נדר. neder. *Stam:* סתם. stam. *Ba be'chovah:* בא
בחובה. ba be'chovah. *Amlei:* אמר ליה. Amlei. *Olas nedavah:* עולת נדבה. olas
nedavah. *Rabbi:* רבי. Rebbi. *Torah:* תורה. Torah. *Gemara:* גמרא. Gemara. *Mishnah:* משנה.
mishnah. *Bechoros:* בכורות. Bechoros. *Temurah:* תמורה. temurah. *Hekdesha:* הקדשה. hekdesha. *Shelamim:* שלמים.
Shelamim. *Rabbi Meir:* רבי מאיר. Rabbi Meir. *Rabbi Yehuda:* רבי יהודה. Rabbi
Yehuda. *Rabbi Shimon:* רבי שמעון. Rabbi Shimon. *Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak:* רב
נחמן בר יצחק. Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak. *Rava:* רבא. Rava. *Rashi:* רש"י.
Rashi. *Pasuk:* פסוק. pasuk. *Ma'aser:* מעשר. ma'aser. *Halacha:* הלכה. halacha. *Chiddush:* חידוש.
chiddush. *In:* אין. In. *Daf:* דף. daf. *Neder:* נדר. neder. *Stam:* סתם.
stam. *Ba be'chovah:* בא בחובה. ba be'chovah. *Amlei:* אמר ליה. Amlei. *Olas
nedavah:* עולת נדבה. olas nedavah. *Rabbi:* רבי. Rebbi. *Torah:* תורה. Torah. *Gemara:*
גמרא. Gemara. *Mishnah:* משנה. mishnah. *Bechoros:* בכורות. Bechoros. *Temurah:* תמורה. temurah. *Hekdesha:*
הקדשה. hekdesha. *Shelamim:* שלמים. Shelamim. *Rabbi Meir:* רבי מאיר. Rabbi Meir. *Rabbi
Yehuda:* רבי יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda. *Rabbi Shimon:* רבי שמעון. Rabbi Shimon. *Rav
Nachman bar Yitzchak:* רב נחמן בר יצחק. Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak. *Rava:*
רבא. Rava. *Rashi:* רש"י. Rashi. *Pasuk:* פסוק. pasuk. *Ma'aser:* מעשר. ma'aser. *Halacha:*
הלכה. halacha. *Chiddush:* חידוש. chiddush. *In:* אין. In. *Daf:* דף. daf. *Neder:*
נדר. neder. *Stam:* סתם. stam. *Ba be'chovah:* בא בחובה. ba be'chovah. *Amlei:*
אמר ליה. So the גמרא Gemara says, okay, that is considered בא
בחובה ba b'chovah because at least you are obligating yourself even if
you didn't formally bind yourself, you didn't say הרי זו, harei zo,
you put yourself in that position to have to bring it. So
then what is not בא בחובה? ba b'chovah? So let's keep on
reading. So the גמרא Gemara says like this: אלא לא נצרכה אלא
לעולת הבאה מן המותרות. ela lo nitzrecha ela l'olat ha-ba'ah min ha-motarot.
The case is that an עולה olah comes from leftover. What does
leftovers mean? You remember that if you have a חטאת chatat with
normally if I have a חטאת chatat that I wasn't able to
bring, I brought another one, whatever, I have to let the חטאת
chatat die. If I have an אשם asham that I brought another
one with, the אשם asham becomes an עולה. olah. Now there's ways
in which חטאת chatat money can also become an עולה. olah. Let's
say for example I set aside a hundred dollars for a חטאת
chatat and I sanctify it with קדושת חטאת kedushat chatat and I
get a sale and I only had to spend ninety dollars for
my sheep. What's the status of that ten dollars? So the remaining
ten dollars is מותרות, motarot, is leftover money, and the הלכה halacha
is it goes towards an עולה. olah. Okay, now we're going to
say in a minute that there's a question what type of an
עולה olah do I do when חטאת chatat or אשם, asham, חטאת
chatat money or אשם asham transforms into an עולה. olah. Some say
it means a personal עולה, olah, my עולה. olah. Some say it
means an עולת ציבור olat tzibur that the ציבור tzibur brings in.
Now עולת ציבור olat tzibur is not relevant because you anyway can't
bring תמורה tmurah from a קרבן ציבור. korban tzibur. So we're assuming
that it's my personal עולה. olah. And that is what we are
saying when that money has to now be used as an עולה,
olah, that is considered it's not בא בחובה. ba b'chovah. Why? Because
I can, it's a little bizarre. On one hand it actually is
בא בחובה, ba b'chovah, it started with a חטאת chatat and an
אשם, asham, which actually is an obligation. Okay, but the point is
I could never have put myself in the position where I obligate
myself to, you know, to be have to bring this leftover money.
It's always like an accidental situation. So because it's always sort of
an accidental situation, it's never something that's done consciously undertaken, that's considered
not בא בחובה. ba b'chovah. It's a very sort of unusual concept
that we would frame that as בא בחובה. ba b'chovah. But somehow
the point is, I mean, here's another way to set it. It
is not an intentional sanctification. Okay, if something is intentionally sanctified, then
you have תמורה. tmurah. If something sort of became an עולה olah
because I had, in a way it's funny, in a way you
actually call it a חובה, chovah. I had no choice, it was
leftover money, I couldn't use it, I have to use it this
way, but it wasn't intentional, then for that type of a thing
you do not bring a, you cannot do a תמורה. tmurah. So
that's what we're excluding. Now let's take a look at this. מאי
קסבר? mai kasavar? What does he hold? אי קסבר למאן דאמר מותרות
לנדבת ציבור, ei kasavar k'man d'amar motarot l'nidvat tzibur, if we say
the leftover money goes to a קרבן ציבור, korban tzibur, an עולה
olah that's קרבן ציבור, korban tzibur, you so you don't give it
over to the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash and they bring an עולה,
olah, so then why do you need to exclude it? פשיטא דלא
עביד תמורה, pshita d'lo avid tmurah, of course it doesn't make a
תמורה. tmurah. דאין תמורה בציבור, d'ein tmurah b'tzibur, there's no תמורה tmurah
by a קרבן ציבור. korban tzibur. אלא רבי שמעון סבירא ליה כמאן
דאמר מותרות לנדבת יחיד אזלי. ela Rabbi Shimon sevira leih k'man d'amar
motarot l'nidvat yachid azli. Fine, he would assume that the leftover money
goes, I can use it for my own personal קרבן. korban. I
bring it myself individually. But nevertheless, since it's something that happened not
intentionally, it happened because accidental, therefore you cannot make, you don't make
a תמורה tmurah by it. Now, מאן שמעת ליה האי סברא? man
sham'at leih hai sevara? רבי אליעזר. Rabbi Eliezer. Who normally is the
one that we have heard normally says that this leftover money goes
for an individual קרבן? korban? That's רבי אליעזר. Rabbi Eliezer. הא שמעינן
ליה בהדיא דעביד תמורה. ha sham'inan leih be-hedya d'avid tmurah. But the
exact same רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer that says the leftover money from
a חטאת chatat and an אשם asham is an individual קרבן, korban,
he actually says that you can make a תמורה tmurah by that.
How do you know that? דתניא, d'tanya, we learn in the ברייתא.
braita. עולה הבאה מן המותרות, olah ha-ba'ah min ha-motarot, you're bringing this
עולה olah from the leftover אשם asham or חטאת chatat money. עושה
תמורה דברי רבי אליעזר. oseh tmurah divrei Rabbi Eliezer. רבי אליעזר Rabbi
Eliezer says it makes a תמורה. tmurah. So now we've got a
problem, right? In order for רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon to need to
exclude it, the whole need to exclude it means he assumed that
it's an individual קרבן. korban. That we know is a position of
רבי אליעזר. Rabbi Eliezer. But the exact same רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer
says that because it's an individual קרבן korban it can do a
תמורה. tmurah. So the גמרא Gemara is obviously going to say fine,
you know, he splits his votes. רבי שמעון סבר לה כוותיה בחדא
ופליג עליה בחדא. Rabbi Shimon savar lah kavateih b'chada u-palig aleih b'chada.
He agrees with him with one, he agrees that it's an individual
קרבן, korban, but he disagrees. רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer says because it's
individual it makes a תמורה, tmurah, רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon learns from
מעשר ma'aser that it does not make a תמורה. tmurah. דרבי אליעזר
סבר עולה הבאה מן המותרות עושה תמורה. d'Rabbi Eliezer savar olah ha-ba'ah
min ha-motarot oseh tmurah. רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer holds that this עולה
olah that this you do from leftover money is an individual קרבן
korban and can do a תמורה. tmurah. ואיהו סבר, v'ihu savar, רבי
שמעון Rabbi Shimon says, I agree with you that the that this
the money what you use the money for is an individual קרבן,
korban, but nevertheless אינו עושה תמורה, eino oseh tmurah, I say it
doesn't make a תמורה. tmurah. because I use מעשר *ma'aser* as my
paradigm. So here by the way we see why it matters that
רבי שמעון *Rabbi Shimon* is using מעשר *ma'aser* as his paradigm, because
until this point everybody agreed with all the הלכות *halachos*. The only
person so far he was... it was only a דרשה *drasha* difference.
So but because he's using מעשר *ma'aser*, that teaches him a new
הלכה *halacha* that you exclude this type of an עולה הבאה מן
המותרות *ola haba min hamotarot* assuming that it is a private קרבן
*korban* and you need to exclude it. Okay, and now we are
wrapping up, but if you thought we were out of the... I'm
sorry, so the תנא קמא *Tanna Kamma* then would say... We don't
know. He might say it's excluded because he might say it's a
קרבן ציבור *korban tzibur*, and he might say that it you can
make a תמורה *tmura* like רבי אליעזר *Rabbi Eliezer*. We don't know
what the תנא קמא *Tanna Kamma* of our משנה *mishna* would say.
Now, if you remember a few days ago, I think it was
over שבת *Shabbos* or whatever, Friday, we were having that very fun
case about a אשם *asham* that you transferred, got a מום *mum*,
you transferred, then became an עולה *ola*, it was two degrees removed
from the original. You thought we were done with that? Ha! We're
going to end our פרק *perek* with that. So let's take a
look. So the גמרא *Gemara* says like this: אי הכי *Ei hachi*,
now you're telling me that when a the money becomes an עולה
*ola*, it should not be a תמורה *tmura* according to רבי שמעון
*Rabbi Shimon*. So one minute, הדר בעי *hada ba'ei* רבי אבין *Rabbi
Avin*. רבי אבין *Rabbi Avin*'s question: הפריש אשם להתכפר בו *Hifrisha asham
l'hitkaper bo*, you set aside an אשם *asham* to use as your
קרבן *korban*, והמיר בו *v'himir bo*, and then you did תמורה *tmura*
with it, right? This is according to רבי שמעון *Rabbi Shimon* that
says you cannot do תמורה *tmura* twice, or רבי יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan*'s
read of רבי שמעון *Rabbi Shimon* that you can't do תמורה *tmura*
twice. So and so you did תמורה *tmura* once with this אשם
*asham*, ונתכפר באשם אחר *v'nitkaper b'asham acher*, וניתק זה לעולה *v'nitak zeh
l'ola*, and then you brought another קרבן *korban* and this transformed from
an אשם *asham* to an עולה *ola*, מהו שיחזור וימיר בו *mahu
she'yachzor v'yamir bo*. Can you do it again? So again, if you
remember, there was a position of רבי שמעון *Rabbi Shimon* that says
that you can't do from one תמורה *tmura* to two animals at
the same time. רבי יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan* read that to say you
cannot do twice with the same animal. So then the גמרא *Gemara*
had a fun time figuring out what would define it as twice.
Twice from the original, but let's say it wasn't exactly the original.
So the question was, well let's say it got a blemish and
you transferred it. Then can you do a new תמורה *tmura*? Or
let's say the original קדושה *kedusha* transferred. How did the קדושה *kedusha*
transfer? It started as an אשם *asham*, you brought another one, it
transformed to an עולה *ola*. And the question was, so is that
doing twice with the same or because it transformed, it's a new
animal, it's a new קדושה *kedusha*. Okay, all of that assumes that
you can do תמורה *tmura* when an אשם *asham* becomes an עולה
*ola*. But we've now said that when אשם *asham* becomes an עולה
*ola*, the extra money or the אשם *asham* itself transforms into an
עולה *ola*, according to רבי שמעון *Rabbi Shimon*, the same תנא *Tanna*
we're talking about, according to רבי שמעון *Rabbi Shimon*, you can't do
תמורה *tmura*. So how did we have all of our fun discussion
before? That whole discussion was according to רבי שמעון *Rabbi Shimon*, all
of it assumed that an אשם *asham* can become that when an
אשם *asham* becomes an עולה *ola* it's you can use it for
תמורה *tmura*, but now it's irrelevant because he says that's excluded from
תמורה *tmura*. So let's take a look. אליבא דמאן *Aliba d'man*? Who
is that question according to? אילימא אליבא דרבי שמעון *Eili'ma aliba d'Rabbi
Shimon*, if it's according to רבי שמעון *Rabbi Shimon*, which is like
a funny אילימא *eili'ma*, it is אליבא דרבי שמעון *aliba d'Rabbi Shimon*,
okay, because רבי שמעון *Rabbi Shimon* was the whole one that said
that רבי יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan* said you can't do twice. האמר רבי
שמעון סבירא ליה *Ha'amar Rabbi Shimon s'vira lei*, עולה הבאה מן המותרות
אינו עושה תמורה *ola haba min hamotarot ein osa tmura*. We just
got through saying that according to רבי שמעון *Rabbi Shimon*, if the
money of an if the אשם *asham* itself or the money of
an אשם *asham* becomes an עולה *ola*, it's not usable for תמורה
*tmura*. So the גמרא *Gemara* says, רבי אבין *Rabbi Avin* הכי קמיבעיא
ליה *hachi ka miba'ei lei*. Fine, here's what his question: אם משכחת
תנא דקאי כרבי שמעון *Im mishkachat Tanna d'ka'ei k'Rabbi Shimon*, if you
were to find an opinion out there, I don't know such an
opinion exists, but hypothetically if there were an opinion out there that
holds like רבי שמעון *Rabbi Shimon* דאמר אין למין וחוזר ומימר *d'amar
ein l'min v'chozer v'meimir*, actually רבי שמעון *Rabbi Shimon* according to רבי
יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan*, that you can't do תמורה *tmura* twice with the
same animal, וסבירא ליה כרבי אליעזר *v'svira lei k'Rabbi Eliezer* דאמר עולה
הבאה מן המותרות עושה תמורה *d'amar ola haba min hamotarot osa tmura*,
and also holds that it's possible to do תמורה *tmura* when an
אשם *asham* transforms into an עולה *ola*, מהו שיחזור וימיר בו *mahu
she'yachzor v'yamir bo*. Now I want to know what happens, which by
the way will actually the גמרא *Gemara* does do that, which is
a beautiful example of how the גמרא *Gemara* sometimes raises questions because
they're conceptually interesting even if which you get a sense of the
גמרא *Gemara* doing all the time, even if they're not relevant להלכה
*l'halacha*. So that's basically what he's saying. He's saying, oh, so now
we're saying that you can't do it twice. Let me figure out
what would define twice. Would it be if you transferred it, would
it be if it transformed? Now the fact that there's no particular
opinion we know that both says you can't do it twice and
that you can do it when it's transformed, that's not so relevant.
I'm more interested in the conceptual question, which is exactly what the
גמרא *Gemara* is always doing. So I actually love this גמרא *Gemara*
because it's quite honest that it's not really about, you know, in
at least some of the time, about להלכה *l'halacha* questions, it's about
the sort of conceptual issue here. Okay, so assuming that I have
an opinion that you can't do it twice, which I know is
רבי שמעון *Rabbi Shimon*, and assuming I have another opinion that rejects
that disagrees with רבי שמעון *Rabbi Shimon* and says that when it
transforms from an אשם *asham* to an עולה *ola* you can do
תמורה *tmura*, then I want to know what happens when it transforms,
is that considered twice or not twice. Did רבי יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan*
agree with that part of רבי שמעון *Rabbi Shimon* as well? What?
Right, I mean yeah, you'd have to say that yeah. Well, רבי
יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan* was... another opinion that rejects that disagrees with רב
שמעון *Rav Shimon* and says that when it transforms from an אשם
*Asham* to an עולה *Olah* you can do תמורה *Temurah* then I
want to know what happens when it transforms is that considered twice
or not twice? Yeah but רבי יוחנן *Rebbe Yochanan* agreed with that
part of רב שמעון *Rav Shimon* as well. What? Right. I mean
yeah you'd have to say that. Yeah. Well yeah but רבי יוחנן
*Rebbe Yochanan* was just interpreting רב שמעון *Rav Shimon* not פוסק *Paskening*.
Okay. So if you were to find such an opinion מהו שיחזור
וימיר בו *Mahu she-yachzor ve-yamir bo* can you do it again? בשני
גופין בקדושה אחת מאי *Be-shnei gufin bi-kedushah achas mai*? First of all
what if it's the same קדושה *kedushah* but another body? Let's say
it got a מום *mum* and you transferred it then would that
be considered twice? It's a different body but the same קדושה *kedushah*.
Would that be have the limit of twice? ואם תמצא לומר *Ve-im
timtzo lomar* קדושה אחת *kedushah achas* then if you say that that
case you are limited that is twice because it's the same sanctity
אלא שתי קדושות וגוף אחד מאי *ella shtei kedushos ve-guf echad mai*?
What if it's the same body but it transformed קדושה *kedushah* an
אשם *Asham* became an עולה *Olah* and assuming again that you could
do תמורה *Temurah* with an אשם *Asham* with an אשם *Asham* that
became an עולה *Olah* what would be the story? Would that be
considered the same or different? Would you be able to do would
that be considered twice or not? And it says תיבעי *Tibai* that
remains a question. I should say by the way normally what's the
word the גמרא *Gemara* uses when it doesn't have an answer? תיקו
*Teiku*. This again the phrase תיבעי *Tibai* is again this other sort
of version that's floating around in תמורה *Temurah* which is more again
as רש"י *Rashi* says ירושלמי *Yerushalmi* more of an ארץ ישראל *Eretz
Yisrael* Aramaic that the word is תיבעי *Tibai* instead of תיקו *Teiku*.
It has the exact same meaning it's a different type of of
a word. הדרן עלך הכל ממירין *Hadran alach hakol memirin*. So with
that we end that פרק *perek* and figure out the objects and
the people that can do תמורה *Temurah*.